Guide to the Max Nomad Papers TAM.017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max Nomad Papers
1902-1967
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Nomad, Max
TAM.017
2.25 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Max Nomad (1881-1973) philosophic anarchist, author and educator, who also wrote under the pseudonym Max Norton was born in 1881 in Buczacz, Poland. He was influenced by the thought of Waclaw Machajski, a heretical Polish radical. Prior to WWI he was a native of Austria and attended the University of Vienna. A Guggenheim Fellow in 1937, and for many years a lecturer in politics and history at New York University, the New School for Social Research and the Rand School, his books include Rebels and Renegades, Apostles of Revolution; Dreamers, Dynamiters and Demagogues; Political Heretics from Plato to Mao Tse-Tung; A Skeptics Political Dictionary and Handbook for the Disenchanted; and Aspects of Revolution. The papers contain manuscripts, clippings, a scrapbook, published material, and course descriptions. The material concerns communism, Latin America, world prominent radicals, and personal philosophy. There is also an unpublished biography of Stalin, notes on the Soviet Union and the Communist Party thereof, and essays.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Max Nomad, 1966 and 1967. The accession number associated with this gift is 1966.001.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Max Nomad (1881-1973) philosophic anarchist, author and educator, who also wrote under the pseudonym Max Norton, was born in Buczacz, Poland. He was influenced by the thought of Waclaw Machajski, a heretical Polish radical. Prior to WWI he was a native of Austria and attended the University of Vienna. A Guggenheim Fellow in 1937, and for many years a lecturer in politics and history at New York University, the New School for Social Research and the Rand School, his books include Rebels and Renegades, Apostles of Revolution; Dreamers, Dynamiters and Demagogues; Political Heretics from Plato to Mao Tse-Tung; A Skeptics Political Dictionary and Handbook for the Disenchanted; and Aspects of Revolution.
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain manuscripts, clippings, a scrapbook, published material, and course descriptions. The material concerns anarchism, communism, Latin America, world prominent radicals, and personal philosophy. There is also an unpublished biography of Stalin, notes on the Soviet Union and the Communist Party thereof, and essays.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Stalin Biography and Notes on the U.S.S.R and Communist Party of the Soviet Union
II, Writings by Max Nomad and Others
Clippings (information artifacts); Anarchism.; Communism.; Soviet Union -- Politics and government.; Anarchists |z United States.; Manuscripts (document genre); Scrapbooks.; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.); Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.; Rand School of Social Science; New York University; Nomad, Max; Norton, Max.; Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza; Nomad, Max
- Series 1: Stalin Biography and Notes on the U.S.S.R and Communist Party of the Soviet Union
  - The Son of the Cobbler (ms, 246 pp.), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stalin (ms, 251 pp.), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stalin: Notes on, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Soviet Union and the Communist Party of the Soviet Union: Notes On; Part I., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Soviet Union and the Communist Party of the Soviet Union: Notes On: Part II., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Soviet Union and the Communist Party of the Soviet Union: Notes On: Part III., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Soviet Union and the Communist Party of the Soviet Union: Notes On: Part IV., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Writings by Max Nomad and Others.
  - The Anarchist Tradition and Other Essays (ns, 198 pp.)Chapters: The knows and the know-nots; Varieties of socialism and anarchism; Russia before and after 1917; Americana; History's bloody pages; Miscellanea., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Aspects of Revolt (mn; New York: New York Bookman Associates), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Balkan Problems Past and Present (as Stephen Naft), 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Berlin People's Free Theater, ca.1910s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Brave New World (pp. 100-123 of unknown ms), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Burnham, Louis: Notes On, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Introduction, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 1-53, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 54-91, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 92-148, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 149-198, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 199-258, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Pages 259-321, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, original): Appendices I-VI, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Introduction, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 1-53, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 54-91, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 92-148, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 149-198, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 199-258, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Pages 259-321, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Carlo Tresca: Rebel Without Uniform" (ms, photocopy): Appendices I-VI, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Clouds over Yugoslavia - by Solomon Schwartz, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dreamers, Dynamiters and Demagogues (ms, New York: Waldon Press), ca.1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Fascism, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jews in Latin America, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Jews in New York, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Juvenilia (scrapbook of published and unpublished writings(, 1902-1921 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Latin America, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lectures and Course Announcements (New School, NYU, Rand School), 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lenin: Notes on, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Personal Letters, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Personal Philosophy, Short Statement of, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Political Heretics from Plato to Mao Tse-Tung (ms; Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press)1963 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Post-Mortems and PostscriptsChapters: Makers of history; Forerunners; Revolutionary romantics of yore; Converts to the new Islam; Giants and clowns; Immortals of shame., 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Spanien und Katalonien: by A. Souchy, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - To the Central Committee [CPUSA]: Dissident letter warning of "Right Danger," by Herbert_____?, Jul 18, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Tragedy of the Underdog. Modern Monthly, Dec 1936 (ms; corrected version), ca.1936 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Trotsky: Notes on, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Writings, Published: Articles, 1935-1949, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)